YWCA of the U.S.A. Records. Record Group 6. Program: Series VII. War Work and Defense Services 324_rg6_s7
Sophia Smith Collection
YWCA of the U.S.A. Records. Record Group 06. Program: Series VII. War Work and Defense Services
1870-2002
Sophia Smith Collection
Young Women's Christian Association of the U.S.A.
324_rg6_s7
14.5 linear feet
This series includes records related to the National Associations work during World War I and World War II, and with defense industries after WWII. Forms part of the YWCA of the U.S.A. Records. Record Group 6. Program.
Arrangement
This Series is divided into three Subseries:
A. WORLD WAR I
B. WORLD WAR II
C. DEFENSE SERVICES
Subseries A. World War I is arranged as follows:
War Work Council
___General and History
___WWC and Executive Committee minutes
___Commission to France
___Committees
___Conference
___Publications
___Training Course
Organizations
Miscellaneous
Oversize
Subseries B. World War II is subdivided as follows:
General and History
Committees
American War-Community Services, Inc.
Japanese Evacuee Project
Oversize
Records of the YWCA's USO activities are included in Subseries C because the YWCA's affiliation with the USO continued for many years after WWII.
Subseries C. Defense Services is arranged as follows:
General and History
United Service Organizations (USO)
United Community Defense Services (UCDS)
Conditions Governing Access
The records are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection without any additional restrictions.
Access to audiovisual materials may first require production of research copies.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The YWCA of the U.S.A. donated a portion of its records to the Sophia Smith Collection in 1964 and the remainder in 2002 and 2003.
Related Materials
This Record group forms part of the YWCA of the U.S.A. Records
NOTE: For the most part, the Microfilmed Records and the Original Format Records do not duplicate each other and both should be consulted. This description covers materials in both formats. See the Contents List for a folder-level inventory of the Original Format Records. See the Microfilmed Records Reel Lists for a detailed inventory of the microfilm.
The Microfilmed Records are much more extensive than those that survive in original format. Unfortunately, reel 152 of the microfilm (Woman's Movement in Labor - World War I, A- Hostess Houses, Fort Benjamin, Indiana) was lost prior to transfer to the Sophia Smith Collection and most of the records on that reel were discarded after filming.
World War I records can be found on the microfilm under: Minutes and Reports -- World War I Subject Files -- World War I
World War II records can be found on the microfilm under: Minutes and Reports -- World War II Subject Files -- National Defense Subejct Files -- War Work-World War II
The Microfilm has early records of USO activities in the Subject Files under War Work, World War II and a few later items under U.S.O.
Extensive coverage of the World War I work is in The AssociationMonthly/Womans Press/YWCA Magazine in SERIES VI. PUBLICATIONS. Records about the sale of properties acquired for War Work (WWI) can be found in RECORD GROUP 3. NATIONAL ADMINISTRATIVE OFFICE in SERIES III. BUILDINGS AND PROPERTIES.
The World War I work was documented extensively in photographs. These can be found in RECORD GROUP 9. PHOTOGRAPHS.
Some information about World War I properties, Centers, and Hostess Houses can be found in the Local Associations Files on the Microfilm. See RECORD GROUP 8. COMMUNITY ASSOCIATIONS, SERIES IV.
Records related to advocacy to end race discrimination in the armed forces and forced relocation and resettlement of Japanese-Americans are in SERIES III. PUBLIC ADVOCACY.
There are additional USO files in the Organizations files in SERIES I of RECORD GROUP 3. NATIONAL ADMINSTRATIVE OFFICE.
Photographs of Defense Services work are in RECORD GROUP 9. PHOTOGRAPHS
The AssociationMonthly/Womans Press/YWCA Magazine in SERIES VI. PUBLICATIONS of RECORD GROUP 6 is an excellent source for most topics.
Because it was the "representative and executive" committee of the National Association, the National Board's minutes should also be consulted when researching YWCA. See RECORD GROUP 2.
These personal papers collections in the Sophia Smith Collection contain materials relevant to the YWCA's WWI-related work: Kate Hillis Boyd Papers, Carolyn Adelia Boynton, Bessie Boies Cotton, Elizabeth Dickerson, Clara Taylor, and Ruth Woodsmall.
The Sophia Smith Collection holds personal papers of a number of YWCA women who worked closely with the USO, these include: Polly Feustal, Virginia Heim George, Ina Ruth Hillis Lackey, and Elisabeth Luce Moore.
Additional Records of the YWCA's USO work are in the Social Welfare History Archives at the University of Minnesota.
Biographical / Historical
YWCA in WORLD WAR I
When the U.S. entered World War I, the YWCA joined the "Committee of Eleven" organizations that banded together as the United War Work Campaign, Inc., to raise and distribute funds to aid war relief efforts at home and abroad. (Though the group originally included eleven organizations, that number eventually settled at seven, including the American Library Association, YMCA, YWCA, National Catholic War Council, Knights of Columbus, Jewish Welfare Board, Salvation Army, and War Camp Community Service.) As the only women's organization in the Campaign, the YWCA's charge was to meet the special needs of women and girls affected by the war. The YWCA raised money, recruited war workers, expanded its existing work in places which already had YWCAs and constructed new facilities in other places, such as camps and bases where soldiers were mobilized and centers where young women were mobilized for agricultural, industrial, and government work. The War Work Council established Industrial War Service Centers or "blue triangle" houses in the U.S. and Foyers des Allees in France where women working in war industries could meet, get good food, relax, entertain guests and participate in wholesome recreation. It also built Hostess Houses where servicemen could visit with their wives, mothers, and friends. Work in these centers continued through the period of active conflict, and the following influenza epidemic and demobilization. Due to the perceived inappropriateness of white women providing recreational services for Black servicemen and industrial women, the YWCA established separate "colored" Industrial Service Centers and Hostess Houses. The was "made evident the deplorable lack of facilities for recreation and amusement" of African-American women and girls who were entering industry in large numbers. In response, the National Association facilitated a substantial expansion of the number of "Colored" Associations and Branches in cities. This dramatic increase of staff and program for African-Americans, was directed from the national office by Eva Bowles and the War Work Council's Colored Work Committee. A national staff which had consisted of two Black secretaries in 1917, grew to thirteen in 1919. At the local level, the number of "Colored" Branches increased from sixteen to forty-nine and secretaries from nine to ninety-nine. World War I precipitated a significant increase in both the size and complexity of the national program of "Work with Foreign-Born Women." The war changed American attitudes toward its immigrant population, suddenly making "every foreign home a place of dread and fear and suspicion." (Edith Terry Bremer, Report to War Work Council, 17 October 1917) Noting that the effects of the war were even more severe for foreign-born women, what had been essentially a northeastern U.S. operation, was nationalized. Multi-lingual secretaries were hired for Port Work, meeting immigrant women at points of intake on the east and west coasts. Staff of a new International Information and Service Bureau translated all kinds of technical materials and wrote speeches and information sheets in a variety of languages "upon all matters for which they are needing help." Other secretaries did Emergency Field work to help speed the opening of new International Institutes for young women of all nationalities. A Bureau was established to help in locating refugee relatives in Europe and the YWCA provided "home service" for the families of enlisted men. To facilitate all this new work and reconstruction work in Europe, the YWCA established training programs for foreign community workers and reconstruction volunteers. Other War Work Council Committees coordinated programs to find housing for women workers who had left home to work at camps and in industry, for women agricultural workers, and for matching volunteer workers with jobs. The Committee on Organization and Extension of Regular Work analyzed where special war work could connected with the regular city work. Staff specialists in topics such as Recreation and Pageantry and Drama, helped Community Associations develop classes and activities for relaxation during uncertain times. The YWCA's Bureau of Social Morality, formed in 1913, was a corps of women medical doctors trained to give sex education lectures. Concerned in particular about young women in the communities adjacent to army camps, the YWCA recruited and trained many more speakers who delivered over 2,000 lectures in 1917-18. During reconstruction, the YWCA enlarged the Bureau's mission to include lectures on general health topics, such as nutrition and hygiene, and rechristened it the Bureau of Social Education. The U.S. YWCA did similar work overseas during the war in Belgium, Czechoslovakia, France, Italy, the Near East, Poland, Romania, and Russia. War workers established centers "to help keep women fit for their work" by providing opportunities for rest, relaxation, and a good meal at a reasonable price. A special group of "Polish Gray Samaritans" served as nurses' aides for Polish soldiers fighting in France. Once the war was over the focus of the work shifted to reconstruction and aid for refugees. The "Polish Grays" concentrated their efforts in Poland. After the Armistice, the Continuation Committee (1919-22) and the Post-Continuation Committee (1921-22) kept much of the work begun by the War Work Council going using War Fund money. The rapid expansion of the War Work significantly changed the YWCA. It experienced what was described as fifteen years' growth in two. Many new Community Associations and Branches were formed and the existing emphasis of the work in many Associations changed, particularly in response to the influx of Industrial Club members. With the new members came increased expectations of "democratic control of Association policies and program." At the national level, the rapid increase put a huge emphasis on recruitment and training of staff, greatly increased the use of publications to "interpret" the Association, and dramatically broadened its program, both in size and scope. Sustaining such an organization proved impossible once the war was over.
YWCA in WORLD WAR II As had been the case in World War I, the YWCA joined with other organizations to raise money and coordinate "civilian war service projects." Six agencies, the Child Welfare League, Family Welfare Association, National Institute of Immigrant Welfare, National Organization of Public Health Nursing, National Urban League, and YWCA, formed American War-Community Services, Inc. (AW-CS). to provide services to workers in war industries and to civilians left behind. AW-CS presented a combined appeal to War Chests and took responsibility for disbursing funding to member agencies for approved war service projects. After the war, the AW-CS agencies formed a new organization with similar aims called "United Community Defense Services." [see Subseries C. Defense Services] The YWCA also joined the YMCA, National Catholic Community Service, Salvation Army, National Traveler's Aid Association, and Jewish Welfare Board to form the United Service Organizations, Inc. (USO), "to serve those affected by the war." The type of work done by the YWCA was similar to its work during World War I, including rest and relaxation centers and services for women workers, servicemen, and war wives. The National Association also worked with its membership to "mobilize woman power for community service" and raised funds for its World Emergency and War Victims Fund to aid war relief overseas. When the U.S. Government ordered the evacuation of all Japanese-Americans from coastal areas, the YWCA monitored the situation closely, looking for opportunities to help the hundreds of its members who were affected by the relocations. After years of working on "social integration" in Japanese-American communities, it was "accepted as a matter of course that the YWCA would go wherever they went." After initial resistance on the part of the government to having private social agencies operating in the relocation centers, the National Association worked with its interned Japanese-American staff and members to establish YWCAs in the relocation centers. Here the YWCA set up counseling, recreation, group activities, educational opportunities, and service work for the young women interned there. In addition to direct assistance in the Relocation Centers, the YWCA worked to sway public opinion, and pressure the government to provide decent care and protection of people and their property. It also advocated for hearing boards which would allow Japanese-Americans to establish loyalty thereby creating a mechanism for release from internment and for citizens' rights legislation. After the war, the National Association provided "factual and interpretive" information to Community Associations to urge them to assist in Japanese-American resettlement. YWCA Defense Services (post-WWII) After World War II, the YWCA continued its activities "on behalf of men and women of the Armed Forces and their families, and workers in defense industries." A fundraising brochure titled "National Defense and the YWCA" cites the outbreak of war in Korea in the summer of 1950 as the point at which "it became evident…that the U.S. would for many years be forced to maintain a large army." The YWCA's part in this effort consisted of continued participation in the USO, involvement in the successor organization to American War-Community Services, the United Community Defense Services (UCDS), and the United Defense Fund. The National Association established a Defense Services Department in 1950 to coordinate these efforts. UCDS, was formed in the fall of 1950 to "assist in the development of essential health and welfare services to people in communities which are unable to cope adequately with defense-created needs." The YWCA was one of fifteen participating agencies working to help new residents in rapidly growing cities and towns adjacent to defense industries. The aim was to fill gaps in services for a relatively brief period until the cities and towns were able to do so. Formed during World War II, United Service Organizations, Inc., (USO), was a cooperative national program of morale, recreation, and religious work for men in the armed forces and for men and women in defense industries. It was an effort to "provide such activities, facilities, and leadership as will recreate in the community near the camp or industrial center the best of normal life and influence that prevails in the communities from which the men come." It was also a united campaign to raise funds for financing the program. By the late 1950s, UCDS had disbanded and the YWCA's Defense Services Department became the USO Division. By the mid 1970s, the USO's founding agencies began to express concern that the "central structure [of the USO] had grown at the expense of agency participation" and that they no longer had meaningful involvement in the organization. When the USO cut all funding to defray the costs of participation as of January 1, 1977, most of the member agencies, including the YWCA, voted to withdraw from the organization.
During its existence, the YWCA's Defense Services Department went by the following names:
1950-1954 Defense Services Department in YWCA's Community Division
1955-1957 Defense Services Department
1958-1971 USO Division
1972-around 1974 YWCA/USOt
Scope and Contents
Records related to the World War I era work include minutes, reports, and other records of the War Work Council and its many committees; files on the Hostess House program and on individual Hostess Houses; publications; texts of lectures given at a training course for volunteer workers in September 1917; organization files; and various small collections of correspondence, memorabilia, and scrapbooks donated to the National Board Archives by war workers.
The WWI War Work had such a major impact on the work of YWCA that the records are central to understanding the growth and development of the organization. The wide-ranging effects can be seen in the kinds of work the Association did, its techniques, processes, policies, and even its size.
The WWII subseries contains general historical materials (including a 1945 dissertation, "The Nisei in Denver, Colorado: A Study of Personality Adjustment and Disorganization" by Dorothy Takechi, a YWCA staff member who worked in the Granada Relocation Center); committee records, clippings, correspondence, minutes and reports, subject and organization files.
The Japanese Evacuee Project records include illuminating reports by Japanese-American YWCA staff and members, visitation reports by other YWCA staff, and such things as literary magazines, newsletters, and conference reports produced by Relocation Center internees.
The War Services subseries contains general historical materials, minutes, reports, publications, and conference files. The reports tend to have useful source materials attached as exhibits. The bulk of the records relate to USO work, 1940-77.
The War Service subseries contains a small amount of general information about UCDS and some general historical information on the YWCA's overall Defense Services activities, but is primarily records of YWCA participation in USO.
Existence and Location of Copies
While most of the records that were microfilmed were discarded afterwards, portions of the WWII records in this series also appear in the microfilm. Specificially, The Minutes and Reports and a substantial selection of Subject File records (primarily records of the Japanese Evacuee Project) are available on the microfilm, which has beend digitized and is now available online through our digital repository.
Record Groups
The YWCA of the USA Records are arranged as follows:
YWCA of the U.S.A. Records (main record)
RECORD GROUP 1. GENERAL AND HISTORY
RECORD GROUP 2. PREDECESSOR ORGANIZATIONS AND NATIONAL BOARD
RECORD GROUP 3. NATIONAL ADMINISTRATIVE OFFICE
RECORD GROUP 4. NATIONAL CONVENTIONS AND CONFERENCES
RECORD GROUP 5. INTERNATIONAL WORK
RECORD GROUP 6. PROGRAM
___SERIES I. DEPARTMENT, STAFF, AND COMMITTEES
___SERIES II. TRAINING AND PERSONNEL
___SERIES III. PUBLIC ADVOCACY
___SERIES IV. CONSTITUENT GROUPS
___SERIES V. PROGRAM SUBJECTS
___SERIES VI. PUBLICATIONS
___SERIES VII. WAR WORK AND DEFENSE SERVICES
RECORD GROUP 7. STUDENT WORK
RECORD GROUP 8. COMMUNITY ASSOCIATIONS
RECORD GROUP 9. PHOTOGRAPHS
RECORD GROUP 10. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS
Artifacts
The Microfilmed Records
The Oversized Materials
Women and war--United States--History; World War, 1914-1918--War work--France--Sources; World War, 1914-1918--War work--Young Women's Christian Association; World War, 1939-1945--Women--United States; World War, 1939-1945--Japanese Americans; World War, 1939-1945--War work; Cotton, Bessie Boies, 1880-1959; United Service Organizations (U.S.); United States--Armed Forces--Women--History--Sources
- SERIES VII. WAR WORK AND DEFENSE SERVICES
  General
  This is the Contents List for the Original Format Records only. The reel lists for the Microfilmed Records are in a separate file. See Related Materials note for more details.
  - Subseries A. World War I
    Historical note regarding YWCA in WWI
    When the U.S. entered World War I, the YWCA joined the "Committee of Eleven" organizations that banded together as the United War Work Campaign, Inc., to raise and distribute funds to aid war relief efforts at home and abroad. (Though the group originally included eleven organizations, that number eventually settled at seven, including the American Library Association, YMCA, YWCA, National Catholic War Council, Knights of Columbus, Jewish Welfare Board, Salvation Army, and War Camp Community Service.)
    As the only women's organization in the Campaign, the YWCA's charge was to meet the special needs of women and girls affected by the war. The YWCA raised money, recruited war workers, expanded its existing work in places which already had YWCAs and constructed new facilities in other places, such as camps and bases where soldiers were mobilized and centers where young women were mobilized for agricultural, industrial, and government work.
    The War Work Council established Industrial War Service Centers or "blue triangle" houses in the U.S. and Foyers des Allees in France where women working in war industries could meet, get good food, relax, entertain guests and participate in wholesome recreation. It also built Hostess Houses where servicemen could visit with their wives, mothers, and friends. Work in these centers continued through the period of active conflict, and the following influenza epidemic and demobilization.
    Due to the perceived inappropriateness of white women providing recreational services for Black servicemen and industrial women, the YWCA established separate "colored" Industrial Service Centers and Hostess Houses. The was "made evident the deplorable lack of facilities for recreation and amusement" of African-American women and girls who were entering industry in large numbers. In response, the National Association facilitated a substantial expansion of the number of "Colored" Associations and Branches in cities. This dramatic increase of staff and program for African-Americans, was directed from the national office by Eva Bowles and the War Work Council's Colored Work Committee. A national staff which had consisted of two Black secretaries in 1917, grew to thirteen in 1919. At the local level, the number of "Colored" Branches increased from sixteen to forty-nine and secretaries from nine to ninety-nine.
    World War I precipitated a significant increase in both the size and complexity of the national program of "Work with Foreign-Born Women." The war changed American attitudes toward its immigrant population, suddenly making "every foreign home a place of dread and fear and suspicion." (Edith Terry Bremer, Report to War Work Council, 17 October 1917)
    Noting that the effects of the war were even more severe for foreign-born women, what had been essentially a northeastern U.S. operation, was nationalized. Multi-lingual secretaries were hired for Port Work, meeting immigrant women at points of intake on the east and west coasts. Staff of a new International Information and Service Bureau translated all kinds of technical materials and wrote speeches and information sheets in a variety of languages "upon all matters for which they are needing help." Other secretaries did Emergency Field work to help speed the opening of new International Institutes for young women of all nationalities. A Bureau was established to help in locating refugee relatives in Europe and the YWCA provided "home service" for the families of enlisted men. To facilitate all this new work and reconstruction work in Europe, the YWCA established training programs for foreign community workers and reconstruction volunteers.